Guide to the Ernie O'Malley Papers AIA.060
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
- Series XI. Clippings and Publicity, 1895-2002
  - Clippings collected by Ernie O'Malley, 1953-1954 (Box 17, Folder 26)
  - Clippings: Ernie O'Malley Funeral, 1957 (Box 17, Folder 27)
  - Publicity: Raids and Rallies, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 28)
  - Clippings: Book Reviews: Civil War Letters of Ernie O'Malley, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 29)
  - Clippings: Book review: IRA Intellectual, 1998 (Box 17, Folder 30)
  - Clippings: various topics; from Irish Press, The New York Times, The Observer, Sunday Times, 1935-1936, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Publicity on Biography: IRA Intellectual, 1998 (Box 17, Folder 31)
- Series XII. Arts Material, 1918-1955
  Notebooks, notes, works, lectures, clippings, magazine articles, photographs, postcards, reprints of artwork, brochures, sketches, exhibition catalogues, theatre programs and printed materials reflecting O'Malley's interest in painting, sculpture, architecture, archeology, music and theatre throughout Europe, Mexico and the United States. Many of the clippings, magazine articles and reprints were collected by O'Malley as research for his articles and essays on painting, sculpture, archeology, architecture and other related topics. A substantial number of art catalogues and theatre programs were deposited at University College Dublin by O'Malley's son, Cormac O'Malley, in 1974. Photocopies of the aforementioned items remain in this series, along with nearly 50 original art catalogues and theatre programs. Also included in this series are more than 200 copies of photographs taken by O'Malley, Helen Hooker O'Malley and others from Mexico and Ireland. Of special interest are notes taken by O'Malley during a series of interviews he conducted with organizers of the Irish Exhibition of Living Art during the 1940s. O'Malley's interest in art criticism encouraged him to embark on series of interviews with some of Ireland's most prominent modern artists including, Evie Hone, Jack Hanlon, Louis le Brocquy, Norah McGuinness, Nano Reid and many others. Works by other authors are filed at the end of this series.
  - Art Materials: Index, 2010 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Catalogues: England I, 1942-1955 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Catalogues: England II, 1942-1955 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Catalogues: Ireland I (copies), 1936-1944 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Catalogues: Ireland II (copies), 1936-1944 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Catalogues: Ireland I (copies), 1945-1951 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Catalogues: Ireland II (copies), 1945-1951 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Catalogues: Ireland III (copies), 1945-1951 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Catalogues: England I, 1939-1948 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Catalogues: England II, 1939-1948 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Catalogues: England III, 1939-1948 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Catalogues: France, 1946 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Catalogues: Ireland I, 1926-1951 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Catalogues: Ireland II, 1926-1951 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Catalogues: Ireland III, 1926-1951 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Catalogues: Italy, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Catalogues: United States, 1928 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Clippings: French Art, 1946-1947 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Clippings: Irish Art and Artists I, undated (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Clippings: Irish Art and Artists I, undated (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - Clippings: Mexican Art and Artists (in Spanish), 1931 (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - Clippings: Mexican Art and Artists, 1928-1949 (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - Clippings: Mexican Art and Artists, 1943-1947 (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - Clippings: European Painting and Sculpture I, undated (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Clippings: European Painting and Sculpture II, undated (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - Clippings: European Painting and Sculpture III, undated (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - Clippings and reprints: European Painting and Sculpture I, undated (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - Clippings and reprints: European Painting and Sculpture II, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Clippings and reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture I, 1926-1946 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Clippings and reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture II, 1926-1946 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Clippings and reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture III, 1926-1946 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Clippings and reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture IV, 1926-19746 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Clippings and reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture I, 1927-1950 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Clippings and reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture II, 1927-1950 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Clippings and reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture III, 1927-1950 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Clippings and reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture IV, 1927-1950 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Notebook: European Art History, 1937-1938 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Notebook: Irish Archeology and History, undated (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Notebook: Archeology and Architecture, 1921-1947 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Notes: Art - European Painting, 1937, undated (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Notes: Art - European Painting, circa 1936-1937 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Notes: Art - European Painting, undated (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Notes: Art - Florentine Drawings, undated (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Notes: Art - French Artists, circa 1946-1947 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Notes: Art - "History of Modern Art", circa 1944-1948 (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Notes: Art - Interviews with Irish Authors, circa 1945 (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Notes: Art - Irish Art and Artists, undated (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Notes: Art - Italian Art and Artists, circa 1925-1926 (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Notes: Art - Mexican Art, Artists and Archeology, 1930-1947 (Box 20, Folder 22)
  - Notes: Art - Mexican Travels, 1931 (Box 20, Folder 23)
  - Notes: Art - various topics, 1932-1945 (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - Notes: Irish History, circa 1938-1946 (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - Notes: Music, circa 1938-1946 (Box 20, Folder 26)
  - Notes: Art - various I, circa 1938-1946 (Box 20, Folder 27)
  - Notes: Art - various II, circa 1938-1946 (Box 20, Folder 28)
  - Photographs: Early Christian Sculpture and Architecture I, undated (Box 20, Folder 29)
  - Photographs: Early Christian Sculpture and Architecture II, undated (Box 20, Folder 30)
  - Photographs: Early Christian Sculpture and Architecture III, undated (Box 20, Folder 31)
  - Photographs: French Art and Fashion design, 1947 (Box 20, Folder 32)
  - Photographs: Mexican Art I (copies), 1931 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Photographs: Mexican Art II (copies), 1931 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Postcards: Art (Box 33)
  - Postcards: Art: Portraits; Collections: Louvre (Box 34)
  - Postcards: Art Collections (sets of postcards from museums) (Box 35)
  - Postcards: Art Collections (sets of postcards from museums) British Museum, Musee de Cluny (Paris), undated (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - Postcards: Architecture (divided by country) (Box 36)
  - Postcards B-W: Boats; Events; Landscapes including Europe, Ireland, Les Pyrenees, Mexico, United States; Unidentified; People, Political (Irish); Various; with Writing (by Ernie O'Malley) (Box 37)
  - Printed Materials: Irish Medieval Art and Architecture, 1925, undated (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Printed Materials: Irish Archeology and Ancient Architecture, Pprehistoric crafts, 1918-1936 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Programs: Theatre performances in England, Ireland and United States I (copies), 1925-1951 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Programs: Theatre performances in England, Ireland and United States II (copies), 1925-1951 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Programs: Theatre performances in England, Ireland and United States III (copies), 1925-1951 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Programs: Theatre (originals), 1928-1946 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Reprints: European Painting and Sculpture I, undated (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Reprints: European Painting and Sculpture II, undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Reprints: European Painting and Sculpture III, undated (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Works: Article "Arts in Ireland" draft, 1945-1946 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Works: Article "Fifth Exhibition of LIving Art" (draft), 1947 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Works: Article "Portrait of a Woman" (draft), circa 1946 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Works: Article "Jack B. Yeats" (draft), 1945 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Works: Article "Louis le Brocquy" (draft), 1946 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Works: Review of Exhibition of Evie Hone's works in Dublin (draft), circa 1945 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - Works by Others: Higgins, Sheila E., 1947 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Works by Others: Judge, Eugene of Caher, 1943-1945 (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Works by Others: unknown, circa 1945-1947 (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - Arts Material: Oversize
    - Clippings and Reprints: European Painting and Sculpture, 1929-1946 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture, 1944-1946 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture I, 1927-1950, undated (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture II, 1927-1950, undated (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (A-B), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (C), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (D), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 7)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (E-F), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (G), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (H-K), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 10)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (L-M), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 11)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (N-R), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 12)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (S), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 13)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (T-Z), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 14)
    - Photographs: Early Christian Sculpture and Architecture, undated (Box 39, Folder 15)
- Series XIII. Chronology Files, 1920-1957
  Art exhibition catalogues, theatre programs, clippings, bills, receipts, correspondence, graphic materials and printed matter collected by Ernie O'Malley and organized chronologically by his son, Cormac O'Malley. Items in this series document his routine activities, and some expenses, as well as, many of friends and associates. A number of the items in this series are photocopies of originals housed elsewhere in the collection, but left here for handy chronological reference.
  - Chronology Files: Index, 2010 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - 1920-1923 (Box 21, Folder 22)
  - 1922 (Box 21, Folder 23)
  - 1923 (Box 21, Folder 24)
  - 1924 (Box 21, Folder 25)
  - 1925 (Box 21, Folder 26)
  - 1926 (Box 21, Folder 27)
  - 1927 (Box 21, Folder 28)
  - 1928 (Box 21, Folder 29)
  - 1928-1935 (Box 21, Folder 30)
  - 1929 (Box 21, Folder 31)
  - 1930 (Box 21, Folder 32)
  - 1931 (Box 21, Folder 33)
  - 1932 (Box 21, Folder 34)
  - 1933 (Box 21, Folder 35)
  - 1934 (Box 21, Folder 36)
  - 1935 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - 1936: Letters to Ernie O'Malley (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - 1936 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - 1937 I (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - 1937 II (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - 1938 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - 1939 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - 1940 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - 1941 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - 1942 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - 1943 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - 1944 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - 1945 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - 1946 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - 1947 I (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - 1947 II (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - 1948 (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - 1949 (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - 1950 (Box 22, Folder 19)
  - 1951 (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - 1952 (Box 22, Folder 21)
  - 1953 (Box 22, Folder 22)
  - 1954 (Box 22, Folder 23)
  - 1955 (Box 22, Folder 24)
  - 1956 (Box 22, Folder 25)
  - 1957 (includes clippings of death notice, funeral) (Box 22, Folder 26)
- Series XIV. Subject Files, 1922-2008
  The bulk of this series consists of research notes and correspondence between Cormac O'Malley and individuals, organizations and institutions associated with his father. Other items include correspondence, clippings, brochures, photographs, greeting cards, interview transcripts, audio reels, printed matter and other ephemeral material pertaining to topics or people associated with Ernie O'Malley or his son, Cormac O'Malley. Throughout the course of his research on his father, Cormac O'Malley worked with his father's friends and their descendents, as well as, numerous universities, libraries, biographers and documentary film makers. In 1970, Cormac O'Malley conducted a series of interviews with Madge and Jack Comer, Sigle Humphreys, Thomas and Peggy Malone, Sean Lemass, Peadar O'Donnell and George Gilmore documenting personal accounts and the military experiences of Ernie O'Malley. The transcriptions of these interviews, as well as, three 1/4" audio reels are housed within this series. Of special interest are materials collected by Ernie O'Malley relating to the Irish Press detailing his travels and expenses, in addition to, the funds he raised for the newspaper. Many of the items in this series are photocopies of originals housed elsewhere in the collection.
  The original inventory listed two separate series for Subject Files: American and Non-American; the latter described as: "Correspondence, clippings, brochures, photographs, greeting cards, interview notes, printed matter and other ephemeral material pertaining to topics or people associated with Ernie O'Malley or his son, Cormac O'Malley with an American connection." These have been combined into one alphabetical run.
  - Subject Files: Indices (14 and 14A), 2010 (Box 22, Folder 27)
  - Aiken, Frank, 1982-2005 (Box 22, Folder 28)
  - Andrews, C.S., 2004-2005 (Box 22, Folder 29)
  - Ballads, 1973-2009 (Box 22, Folder 30)
  - Basques, 1926, 1975-2005 (Box 22, Folder 31)
  - Beckett, Samuel, 1983-1995 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Behan, Anthony, 2003-2005 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Book Reviews, 2002-2003 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Brady, Kathleen (Kay), 2006-2008 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Brennan, Maureen, 1993-2004, 2008 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Brennan, Robert, 2008 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC), 1980-1983 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Brown, Paddy (Padraig de Brun), Monsignor (some material in irish), 1935-2000 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Brugha, Cathal and Ruari Brugha, 2005, undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Butler, Pat (RTE Ballyseedy), 1997-1998 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Cashman, Seamus (Liam O'Flaherty), Jan 2008 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Childers, Mary Alden Osgood (Mrs. Erskine) I, 1922-2004 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Childers, Mary Alden Osgood (Mrs. Erskine) II, 1922-2004 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Childers, Mary Alden Osgood (Mrs. Erskine) III (photocopies of letters), 1922-2004 (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - Chronology of Ernie O'Malley 1914-1924 (prepared by Cormac O'Malley), 1982-2003 (Box 23, Folder 15)
  - Citkowitz-Liber, Rebecca, 1947-2006 (Box 23, Folder 16)
  - Clark, Jack: items of JC purchased by EOM in 1955, circa 2003 (Box 23, Folder 17)
  - Clifford-Comer, Madge (assistant to Ernie O'Malley), steno notebooks, circa 1935-1947 (Box 23, Folder 18)
  - Clurman, Harold, 1979 (Box 23, Folder 19)
  - Coffey, Donogh, 1972-1984 (Box 23, Folder 20)
  - Comer Family, 1922-2005 (Box 23, Folder 21)
  - Comerford, James J., 1983 (Box 23, Folder 22)
  - Cooney, Andy, 2004-2006 (Box 23, Folder 23)
  - Craig, Maurice, 2007 (Box 23, Folder 24)
  - Crane, Hart, 1931-2008 (Box 23, Folder 25)
  - Davis, Chester (of Simpson, Thatcher and Barlett, attys) corrsepondence to Helen Hooker O'Malley, 1956 (Box 23, Folder 26)
  - DeValera, Eamon, 1945-2004 (Box 23, Folder 27)
  - Dictionary of Irish Biography (see also Cooney, Andy), 2003-2004 (Box 23, Folder 28)
  - Dodge-Luhan, Mabel (Luhan, Mabel Dodge), 2005 (Box 23, Folder 29)
  - Fitzgerald, Mabel (Mrs. Desmond), 2002-2003 (Box 23, Folder 30)
  - Folklore (on Ernie O'Malley), 2003-2006 (Box 23, Folder 31)
  - Ford, John (Jack) and family, 1951-1985 (Box 23, Folder 32)
  - Gallagher, Frank and Anne, 1957-2004 (Box 23, Folder 33)
  - Gallivan, Thomas and family (also spelled Galivan), 1922-2004 (Box 23, Folder 34)
  - Goddard, Theodora, 1983-2004 (Box 23, Folder 35)
  - Golden, Helen Merriman/-Sax, Eithne, 1928-2005 (Box 23, Folder 36)
  - Golden Family: Ernie O'Malley Letters I, 1928-2005 (Box 23, Folder 37)
  - Golden Family: Ernie O'Malley Letters II (Box 23, Folder 38)
  - Golden Family: Ernie O'Malley Letters I (typed copies of letters), 1928-2005 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Golden Family: Ernie O'Malley Letters II (typed copies of letters), 1928-2005 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Golden Family, 1926-2002 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Golden Family, 1926-2002 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Golden, E / O'Malley, Cormac, 1930-2002 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Golden-Katz, Deidre, 1982-1984 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Golden-Sax, Eithne (mostly clippings), 1957-2006 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Greene, Graham, 1947-2006 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Greene, Graham: Clippings, 1989-2006 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Greenwood, Marion (1909-1970)(NY artist; did a portrait of EOM circa 1933), 1930, 1973 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Halligan-Clarke, Sunniva, 1983 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Henry, Paul, 2007 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Herbert, Robert (Limerick Public Library), 1948-1955 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Holloway, Joseph, 1941 (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Hone, Evie, 1945-1985 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Houghton Miflin Company, 1937 (Box 24, Folder 16)
  - Hughes, John T. and Mary (sister), 1938-1948 (Box 24, Folder 17)
  - Humphreys, Sigle (Sheila, Mrs. Donal O'Donoghue), 1922-1931, 1970-2003, undated (Box 24, Folder 18)
  - Humphreys, Sigle (Sheila, Mrs. Donal O'Donoghue): additional copies, 1922-2003, undated (Box 24, Folder 19)
  - Interviews: Cormac O'Malley (includes 3 reels at end of series), Oct 1970 (Box 24, Folder 20)
  - Irish Pension Board, 2007-2008 (Box 24, Folder 21)
  - Irish Press, Limited I, 1928-1931, 1974 (Box 24, Folder 22)
  - Irish Press, Limited II, 1928-1931, 1974 (Box 24, Folder 23)
  - Irish Times, 1922, 2004 (Box 24, Folder 24)
  - Jeffers, Una and Robinson, 1928, 1993-2006 (Box 24, Folder 25)
  - Johnson, Spud, 2004 (Box 24, Folder 26)
  - Joyce-O'Loughlin, Una, 1964-1985 (Box 24, Folder 27)
  - Kazan, Elia, 2003 (Box 24, Folder 28)
  - Kelleher, John V., 1989, 2001-2002 (Box 24, Folder 29)
  - Kelly, Grace (art critic), 1929-1950 (Box 24, Folder 30)
  - Kelly, P.J., 1978-1984 (Box 24, Folder 31)
  - Kerrigan, Georgette and Sarsfield, 1937-2004 (Box 24, Folder 32)
  - Kerwood, Beatrice, 2005 (Box 24, Folder 33)
  - Killian, Lord Michael, 1982-1984 (Box 24, Folder 34)
  - Kilmainham Jail I, 1921-1991, undated (Box 24, Folder 35)
  - Kilmainham Jail I, 1921-1991, undated (Box 24, Folder 36)
  - Kilmainham Jail Museum and Exhibit, 1987-2003 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Kilmainham Jail Museum and Exhibit, 1998-2007 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Lanvin, Mary, 1983-1985 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Le Brocquy, Louis and Family, 1946-1973 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Lemass, Sean, Oct 1970 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Lennon, Joseph, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Macardle, Dorothy, 1946 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - MacBride, Sean, 1922-1923, 1974-2005 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - MacCarvill, Eileen and Niall, 1970-1999 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - MacEvilly, Michael, 2006-2008 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - MacGreevy, Thomas I, 1947-2007 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - MacGreevy, Thomas II, 1947-2007 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - MacGreevy, Thomas III, 1947-2007 (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - MacHale, Desmond ( The Quiet Man film; handwritten bio of Ernie O'Malley), 1973-2008 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - MacLochlainn, S.D. (nephew of Sean Connolly), 1985 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - MacNiece, Frederick Louis, 2006 (Box 25, Folder 16)
  - Magan, Manchan / Roan / Croine ("The Struggle") I, 1973-2005 (Box 25, Folder 17)
  - Magan, Manchan / Roan / Croine ("The Struggle") II, 1973-2005 (Box 25, Folder 18)
  - Maguire, Tom and family, 2004 (Box 25, Folder 20)
  - Malone, Thomas and Peggy (contemporary of Ernie O'Malley), Oct 1970 (Box 25, Folder 21)
  - Manahan, Liam and family, 1983-2007 (Box 25, Folder 22)
  - Martin, Colbert, 1963-1985 (Box 25, Folder 23)
  - McGahern, John, 2002-2006 (Box 25, Folder 24)
  - McGlynn, Mick, 1964, 1983 (Box 25, Folder 25)
  - McGrail, Jean I, 1978-1983 (Box 25, Folder 26)
  - McGrail, Jean II, 1978-1983 (Box 25, Folder 27)
  - McHugh, Roger and Patricia, 1927-1945 (Box 25, Folder 28)
  - McKay, Francis I (Republican material), 1984-2004 (Box 25, Folder 29)
  - McKay, Francis II, 1984-2004 (Box 25, Folder 30)
  - McKay, Francis III, 1984-2004 (Box 25, Folder 31)
  - McKay, Francis IV, 1984-2004 (Box 25, Folder 32)
  - Meehan, Bernard (Trinity College Library, Manuscripts division), 1989-1991 (Box 25, Folder 33)
  - Metzner, Wolfgang (son of Alfred Metzner, publisher of On Another Man's Wound in German), 1982-1989 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Military Archives, 1922-1923, 2003 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Monroe, Harriet ( Poetry magazine), 1935 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - National Archives of Ireland, 1922-2001 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - National Library of Ireland, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Neenan, Connie (Cornelius), 1972-1984 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Notes and Letters relationg to Ernie O'Malley I (compiled by Cormac O'Malley and copied elsewhere in the collection), 1926, 1949-1989 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Notes and Letters relationg to Ernie O'Malley II (compiled by Cormac O'Malley and copied elsewhere in the collection), 1926, 1949-1989 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry (TG4 documentary), 2006 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry I, 2007 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry II, 2007 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry, 2008 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry: Film Proposal/Drafts I, 2006-2007 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry: Film Proposal / Drafts II, 2006-2007 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - O'Connor, Frank, 1998-2007 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - O'Connor, Ulick, circa 1991 (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - O'Doherty, Joseph (O'Doherty v. O'Malley, copy of judgment), 1937 (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - O'Donnell, James, Jul 193-Aug 1983 (Box 26, Folder 18)
  - O'Donnell, Peadar (interview by Cormac O'Malley also with George Gilmore), 1970-1986 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - O'Dowd, John David, 1985-1986 (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - O'Faolain, Sean, 1983-2004 (Box 26, Folder 21)
  - O'Flaherty, Liam, 1983-2004 (Box 26, Folder 22)
  - O'hAodna, Michael (Oct. 7, no year), circa 1950, undated (Box 26, Folder 24)
  - O'Malley, Ernie I (photocopies of letters), 1930-1955 (Box 26, Folder 25)
  - O'Malley, Ernie II (photocopies of letters), 1930-1955 (Box 26, Folder 26)
  - O'Rahilly, Aodogan "The Flight in Ailesbury Road" recollection, 1998 (Box 26, Folder 27)
  - O'Reilly, Martin, 1973-1984 (Box 26, Folder 28)
  - Piper, John, 1998-2006 (Box 26, Folder 29)
  - Plunkett, Countess (Mary Josephine), 1991 (Box 26, Folder 30)
  - Poetry Magazine (Chicago), 1933-2004 (Box 26, Folder 31)
  - Proud, Ernest W., 1931 (Box 26, Folder 32)
  - Publications (by Ernie O'Malley) I, 1940-1963 (Box 26, Folder 33)
  - Publications (by Ernie O'Malley) II, 1940-1963 (Box 26, Folder 34)
  - Radio Telefis Eireann, 1982-2008 (Box 26, Folder 35)
  - Raleigh, John, 1939-2008 (Box 26, Folder 36)
  - References to Ernie O'Malley - in books, articles and publications I, 1936-2006, undated (Box 26, Folder 37)
  - References to Ernie O'Malley - in books, articles and publications II, 1936-2006, undated (Box 26, Folder 38)
  - Reynolds, Lorna (1911-2003); author, 1983-2003 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Robinson, Lennox, 1967, 2005-2006 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Rogers, Fanny, 1974, 1982 (Box 27, Folder 3)